恭喜各位同志们  你们是3828人中的最后一批
Congratulations, comrades. You're the last of 3,828 men.
切尔诺贝利
前情提要
这是我在国家档案馆里找到的
I found this in the state archive.
我需要你的帮助
I need your help.
你能否确认反应堆爆炸
Can you confirm that the reactor exploded
发生在他们执行停堆操作之后
after they attempted to shut it down?
怎么  你觉得问对了问题
What, you think the right question
就能得到真相吗
will get you the truth?
他们要审判迪亚特洛夫
They're going to put Dyatlov on trial.
我们会被传唤  作为专家证人
We're going to be asked to give expert testimony.
我分析了数据
I've analyzed the data.
他们关闭了反应堆  然后就爆炸了
They shut the reactor down, and then it exploded.
你之前看过这个
You've seen this before.
我真不知道这会导致爆炸
I had no idea it could cause an explosion.
-所以是他们的错吗  -是的
- So, it is their fault? - Yes.
但不全是他们的错
But not only their fault.
我们可以和克格勃谈条件
We can make a deal with the KGB.
你去维也纳时不要提及这事
You'll leave this information out in Vienna.
克格勃会私下让我们修好剩下的反应堆
They quietly let us fix the remaining reactors.
原创翻译  双语字幕
最新连载海外影视剧下载
请登陆 www.YYeTs.com
仅供交流学习  禁止商用盈利
你有机会向全世界发声
You have a chance to talk to the world.
得有人说出真相
Someone has to start telling the truth.
翻译     草草  苏小黛  Eunice  elingbow  哈里不是波特
翻译     马丁马丁回音山  tong大梨  小胖橘子  DerbyNinja  白夜君
翻译     放开那个方丈  苏葵  Margaeryy  Sakura的小书包  伊森泽生
顾问     elingbow
校对     草草  苏葵
时间轴     荞麦麦  啾啾啾 想念Gallifrey的Wholock  Caroline
后期     拉图
总监     苏葵
1986年4月25日  普里皮亚季
爆炸发生12小时前
我听说布卡诺夫可能要升官
I hear they might promote Bryukhanov.
我们在安全测试上遇到的小麻烦
This little problem we have with the safety test...
如果能成功完成
if it's completed successfully,
是的  那他很可能会升官
yes, I think promotion's very likely.
谁知道  或许去莫斯科
Who knows, maybe Moscow.
当然了  他走后  就是我负责
Naturally, they'll put me in charge once he's gone,
那我就得找个人接替我
and then I'll need someone to take my old job.
我可以选斯特尼考夫
I could pick Sitnikov.
我希望能被考虑
I would like to be considered.
我会记着的
I'll keep that in mind.
维克多·佩丘维奇
Viktor Petrovich,
测试的准备工作进展顺利
preparations for the test have gone smoothly.
迪亚特洛夫同志在按照我的指示准备
Comrade Dyatlov's been working per my instructions,
4号反应堆的输出也已降至1600兆瓦
and Reactor 4 output's been reduced to 1600 megawatts.
如果你批准  我们就可以继续降低...
With your approval, we're ready to continue lowering power to--
我们得暂缓
We have to wait.
什么
Is, uh...?
你是要问我出什么问题了吗  尼克莱
Are you going to ask me if there's a problem, Nikolai?
表情看不懂啊
You can't read a fucking face?
三年了  我一直想完成测试
Three years, I've tried to finish this test.
三年了
Three years.
我刚接到基辅电网负责人的电话
I've just had a call from the grid controller in Kiev.
他说  我们不能继续降低电力
He says we can't lower power any further,
至少得再等10小时
not for another ten hours.
电网负责人  他凭什么...
The grid controller? Where does he get off--
这不是他决定的  迪亚特洛夫
It's not the grid controller's decision, Dyatlov.
现在月底了
It's the end of the month.
为了满足产量指标
All the productivity quotas.
大家都在加班工作  工厂需要电力
Everyone's working overtime, the factories need power.
是上面有人给他们压力
Someone's pushing down from above.
但我们是别想知道是谁了
Although, we'll never know who.
我们要取消吗
So, do we have to scrap it or what?
不  不需要
No, I don't think so.
如果我们需要等10小时
If we need to wait ten hours,
-那我们就等  -只有一半功率的话
- we wait. - Running at half power,
不会出现稳定性问题吗
we're not going to have stability issues?
-不  应该不...  -我没问你
- No, I-I should think-- - I'm not asking you.
安全的
It's safe.
我们维持在1600
We'll maintain at 1600.
我回家  睡会儿  晚上再来
I'll go home, get some sleep, come back tonight.
到时进行
We'll proceed then.
我会亲自监督测试
I'll personally supervise the test.
会完成的
And it will be completed.
那我就不留下等了
Well, I'm not waiting around then.
完成了打给我
Call me when it's done.
切尔诺贝利
第五集[全剧终]
莫斯科
1987年3月
你感觉如何
How do you feel?
你昨天去看了医生
You went to the doctor yesterday.
你的健康情况如何了
How is your health?
你不知道吗
You don't know?
维也纳的报纸
From Vienna.
你会德语吗
Do you read German?
上面写着  "终于有个说实话的苏联科学家了"
It says, "At last a Soviet scientist who tells the truth."
当然了  我讨厌这夹枪带炮的口气
Obviously, I resent the insinuation,
但我觉得可以说
but I think it's fair to say,
你在大会上留下了很不错的印象
you made an excellent impression at the conference.
原来你还蛮擅长这个的
Turns out, you're quite good at this.
什么  撒谎吗
At what? Lying?
是政治手腕  列加索夫  政治
Statecraft, Legasov. Statecraft.
西方现在能接受
The West is now satisfied
切尔诺贝利事故完全是操作失误引起
that Chernobyl was solely the result of operator error,
本质上来说确实是的
which it essentially was.
我们得谢谢你
We have you to thank for that,
我们也打算有所表示
and we intend to.
"苏联英雄奖章"
"Hero of the Soviet Union."
我们的最高荣誉
Our highest honor.
我自己都没得过
They haven't even given it to me.
"升任库尔恰托夫研究所所长"
"Promotion to Director of the Kurchatov Institute."
我受之有愧
I'm humbled.
我觉得你这人
I don't think there's
没那么谦虚  瓦列利·阿列克谢维奇
anything humble about you, Valery Alexeyevich.
这些奖赏目前还不属于你
These rewards are not yours yet.
首先  你要在庭审上作证
First, your testimony at the trial.
佘考夫同志  我明白自己对国家的职责
Comrade Charkov, I understand my duty to the State.
但你向我们保证过
But you gave us assurances.
会让反应堆改进安全
The reactors would be made safe.
已经几个月了  没有任何改变
It's been months, no changes have been made.
-甚至没有任何讨论  -先出庭作证
- No changes even discussed. - First, the trial.
等事情结束  坏人有了
Once it's over, we will have our villains,
英雄有了  真相也有了
we will have our hero, we will have our truth.
之后  我们就可以处理反应堆的事了
After that, we can deal with the reactors.
你坐火车来的吗
Did you take a train?
是的  火车
Yes, I took a train.
咱们还是说说维也纳的事吧
Now let's talk about Vienna.
我不是来斥责你的
I'm not here to scold you.
不管谢比纳怎么说  我知道这世界的规矩
I know how the world works despite what Shcherbina says.
那你为什么来
So... why are you here?
因为我就是个老顽固
Because I'm brutally stubborn.
你也指望我如此
Which you were hoping for.
佘考夫的意思是
Charkov is saying they're
他们等庭审完了就会去修复反应堆
going to fix the reactors after the trial.
你相信他吗
Do you believe him?
政府决不会自愿修复反应堆
The State will never willingly fix the reactors,
因为承认问题就等于承认他们撒了谎
because acknowledging the problem means admitting that they lied.
得逼一逼他们
They will have to be forced.
在庭审上  你要说出实话
At the trial, you're going to tell the truth.
你要说服陪审团
You're going to convince the jury.
庭审只是走个过场
It's a show trial.
陪审团已经知道该如何裁定了
The jury's already been handed their verdict.
我说的不是他们
I'm not talking about them.
中央委员会邀请了
The Central Committee have invited
科学界的人来旁观庭审
members of the scientific community to observe the trial.
那些人是我们的同事  来自库尔恰托夫
Our colleagues, from Kurchatov,
斯雷德玛什  还有能源部
from Sredmash, from Minenergo,
他们会坐在人群中
they will be sitting in
听你说的每一个字
the crowd listening to every word you say.
那是个只有我们知道的陪审团
A jury that only we know is there.
等到你作证时  说到爆炸的那个时刻时
And when your testimony arrives at the moment of the explosion?
那就是我们的陪审团终于得知真相的时刻
That is when our jury will finally hear the truth.
-他们能怎么办  -坚持主张改革
- And do what with it? - Insist on reform.
不仅是RBMK
Not just to the RBMK,
-而是整个核工业  -不不不
- but the entire industry. - No, no, no, no, no.
-没有我们他们无法运作  -不
- They can't function without us. - No, no, no.
如果我们
If we...
你知道沃科夫是什么下场吗
Do you know what happened to Volkov
你发现的那份报告的作者
the man whose report you found?
他们把他从研究所撤职了
They just removed him from his position at the Institute.
因为知情而遭到解雇
Sacked for the crime of knowing.
你觉这些被精挑细选出来
And you think that these scientists,
旁观一场走过场性质的庭审的科学家们
handpicked to witness a show trial,
会受我影响而行动起来
will somehow be stirred into action by me?
就因为我违抗国家  采取了英勇的立场
Because of some heroic stance I take in defiance of the State?
-没错  -为什么
- Yes. - Why?
因为你是瓦列利·列加索夫  你的话有份量
Because you're Valery Legasov, and you mean something.
我也希望如果我把事实说出来就够了
I'd like to think that if I spoke out, it would be enough.
但我知道这世界的规矩
But I know how the world works.
他们会枪毙我的  霍缪克
They will shoot me, Khomyuk.
你叫我查清楚真相
You told me to find out what happened.
我找数十人谈过
I spoke to dozens of people.
我记下了他们说的每一个字
Every word they said, I wrote down.
都在这些笔记本里
All in these books.
这些是还活着的
These are the ones who are still alive.
这些是已经死了的
These are the ones who are dead.
他们为救彼此而死
They died rescuing each other.
为灭火而死  为照顾伤者而死
Putting out fires, tending to the wounded.
他们没有犹豫  也没有动摇
They didn't hesitate, they didn't waiver.
只是做了必须做的事
They simply did what had to be done.
我也是
So have I.
我自愿接近暴露的反应堆
I went willingly to an open reactor.
所以我已经献出了生命
So I've already given my life.
难道还不够吗
Isn't that enough?
很抱歉  但那还不够
No, I'm sorry, but it is not.
切尔诺贝利市
1987年7月
苏联共产党中央委员会
The Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union
及苏联最高苏维埃主席团
and the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the U.S.S.R.
决定代表人民
has determined that justice be carried out
伸张正义
on behalf of the People
这符合由第二十届  二十一届
in accordance with the general goal of our Party
二十二届代表大会所制定的我党总目标
as determined by its 20th, 21st, and 22nd Congresses,
即列宁主义目标
which is a Leninist goal.
无论以前  现在或将来
It was, is, and will be
这都是苏联唯一不变的目标
the only immutable goal in the Soviet state.
我们要坚定不移地
The path of Leninist principles
走马列主义原则道路
shall be consistently and undeviatingly followed
因为这体现了苏维埃人民的切身利益
as it expresses the vital interests of the Soviet People,
希望与决心
its hopes and aspirations
正如它指导了党和国家的工作
as we guide the life of the Party and the State.
本庭开庭
This session of court is now open,
由米兰·卡德尼考夫法官同志主审
Comrade Judge Milan Kadnikov presiding.
现起诉
Indictments:
维克多·布卡诺夫
Viktor Bryukhanov,
安纳托利·迪亚特洛夫
Anatoly Dyatlov,
尼克莱·福明
Nikolai Fomin...
违反苏联刑法
are accused of violating Article 220 Section 2
第二章第220条
of the Criminal Code of the Soviet Union,
导致1986年4月26日发生核灾难
resulting in a nuclear disaster on April 26, 1986.
检方传唤霍缪克同志出庭作证
The State calls witnesses Comrade Khomyuk
她来自白俄罗斯核能源研究所
of the Byelorussian Nuclear Institute,
还有库尔恰托夫原子能研究所的列加索夫同志
Comrade Legasov of the Kurchatov Institute of Atomic Energy,
和鲍里斯·埃夫多基莫维奇·谢比纳同志
and Comrade Boris Evdokimovich Shcherbina,
部长理事会的副主席
Deputy Chairman of the Council of Ministers
兼燃料与能源局局长
and head of the Bureau for Fuel and Energy.
一切从一场安全测试开始
It began with, of all things, a safety test.
当初为什么需要做安全测试
Why was there need for a safety test at all?
事故发生时  4号反应堆已经不新了
Reactor Number 4 was not new when the accident occurred.
事实上  它是在1983年12月20日投入使用的
In fact, it went into operation on December 20th, 1983.
11天后  就在那年的最后一天
Eleven days later, on the last day of the year,
核电站厂长维克多·布卡诺夫签下这份文件
Plant Director Viktor Bryukhanov signed this document--
证实反应堆施工工程完工
certifying the completion of the construction of the reactor.
由于赶在年前结束工作
As a result of finishing the work before the end of the year,
布卡诺夫同志被授予社会主义劳动英雄称号
Comrade Bryukhanov was awarded Hero of Socialist Labor.
福明同志被授予勇敢奖章
Comrade Fomin was awarded for Valorous Labor.
迪亚特洛夫同志被授予红旗勋章
Comrade Dyatlov was given an Order of the Red Banner.
但他们的工作尚未完成
But their work was not finished.
这份文件是伪造的
And this document was a lie.
签署证书之前
In order to sign this certificate,
必须成功完成所有安全测试
all safety tests had to have been successfully completed,
然而有一项未完成
and yet, one remained.
核反应堆中的堆芯会产生热量
A nuclear reactor generates heat in the core here.
这里有多台水泵
A series of pumps, here and here,
以恒定流量驱动冷却水流过堆芯
send a constant flow of cooling water through the core.
堆芯的热量将水转化为蒸汽
The core's heat turns the water to steam,
蒸汽推动汽轮机转动
and the steam spins the turbine here,
从而产生电能
and the result is electricity.
但如果一座电厂失去动力会怎么样
But what if a power plant has no power?
如果电厂本身的供电中断会怎么样
What if the power feeding the plant itself is disrupted?
停电  设备故障
A blackout, equipment failure,
或者遭到外敌袭击
or an attack by a foreign enemy?
如果没有电力
If there's no power,
泵就无法向堆芯供水
the pumps cannot move water through the core.
没有水  堆芯就会过热
And without water, the core overheats,
燃料会熔毁
the fuel melts down.
简而言之  核灾难
In short, a nuclear disaster.
怎么解决
The solution?
这里有三台柴油备用发电机
Three diesel fuel backup generators here.
问题解决了吗
So, problem solved?
没有
No.
布卡诺夫知道问题根本没有解决
Bryukhanov knew that the problem was not solved at all.
备用发电机需要一分钟左右
The backup generators took approximately one minute
才能达到所需转速
to reach the speed required
驱动水泵  避免堆芯熔毁
to power the pumps and prevent a meltdown,
到那时  一切都晚了
and by that time, it would be too late.
下面就来说说安全测试
So we arrive at the safety test.
理论如下  如果设备失去供电
The theory was this: If the facility lost power,
正在转动的汽轮机
the turbine, which had been spinning,
会经过一段时间的减速  最终停机
would take some time to slow down and stop.
如果能将这段时间之内
What if you could take the electricity
它所发出的电能输送给水泵呢
it was still generating and transfer it to the pumps?
如果正在惰转的汽轮机
What if the dying turbine
能够驱动水泵运行足够长的时间
could keep the pumps working long enough
以填补发电机投入前的60秒缺口呢
to bridge the 60-second gap until the generators came on?
有什么问题吗
Any questions?
没有  请继续
No. Continue, please.
为了测试这一理论
To test this theory,
将反应堆置于低功率模式
the reactor is placed in a reduced power mode--
700兆瓦
700 megawatts--
以模拟停电状态
to simulate a blackout condition.
随后使汽轮机停运
Then the turbines are turned off,
在转速逐渐降低的过程中
and as they slowly spin down,
测量其电力输出
their electrical output is measured
判断是否足以驱动水泵运行
to see if it's enough to power the pumps.
科学理论没问题
The science is strong,
但实际效果取决于执行测试的人
but a test is only as good as the men carrying it out.
他们的第一次测试失败了
Now, the first time they tried, they failed.
第二次测试失败了
The second time they tried, they failed.
第三次测试失败了
The third time they tried, they failed.
第四次测试
The fourth time they tried
是在1986年4月26日
was April 26th, 1986.
霍缪克同志
Comrade Khomyuk.
要理解那晚发生了什么
To understand what happened that night,
我们要回到10小时之前
we have to go back ten hours earlier--
回到4月25日  安全测试本该展开的当天
April 25th, the day the test was meant to take place.
下午两点钟
By two in the afternoon,
反应堆的功率已经减少一半
the reactor has been lowered by half
从正常的3200兆瓦
from its normal output level of 3200 megawatts
降到1600兆瓦并保持稳定
to 1600 megawatts and is stable
且已准备好把功率降低到测试要求
and ready to be reduced to its final output level for the test:
700兆瓦
700 megawatts.
但在他们继续之前  来了一个电话
But before they can proceed, there is a phone call.
基辅的电网官员说在午夜之前
Power grid officials in Kiev say that they cannot afford
他们不能承受电力供应的进一步降低了
a further reduction in the electricity until after midnight.
他们要求把测试推后十个小时
They are asking for a ten-hour delay.
这是第一个关键时刻
This is the first critical moment,
灾难的连锁反应的第一环
the first link in the chain of disaster.
称职的管理团队肯定会坚持把测试取消
Competent management would have insisted on canceling the test.
而这三个人却同意让测试继续
These three men allowed it to proceed.
为什么推后会如此危险
Why was this delay so dangerous?
它造成了两个问题
It created two problems:
一个是科学问题
One of them is scientific in nature...
另一个则是人员问题
and the other is very human.
我们先考虑这个
This is the one we will consider first.
午夜有个交接班
At midnight, there is a shift change.
切尔诺贝利
弗拉基米尔·伊里奇·列宁核电站
-霍登楚克  -别想了  你找别人去吧
- Khodemchuk-- - Forget it. Find another fool.
托普特诺夫  想买辆摩托车吗
Toptunov, want to buy a motorcycle?
托普特诺夫  他还是个孩子
Toptunov? He's just a little boy.
他脸上的毛比底下的还多呢
He's got more hair on his face than on his balls.
毛  他嘴唇上是毛吗
Hair? Is that what's on his lip?
列尼德·费罗维奇
Leonid Fedorovych.
阿基莫夫让你尽快去控制室
Akimov says to come to the control room as soon as you can.
-他已经到了  -他来得早
- Is he already here? - He came in early.
是关于测试的事
Something about a test.
看见了吧  像什么样
You see? Desperate.
萨沙
Sasha?
你知道他们本该做的那个测试吗
Ah. You know the test they were supposed to run?
断电后汽轮机惰性发电  他们去年做过
The turbine rundown, they tried it last year.
他们没办法在白班做  所以就交给我们了
They couldn't do it on the day shift, so they've given it to us.
给我们
To us?
我们不知道是...
We don't know what--
-我们根本不知道测试怎么做  -没事
- We don't know what it is. - It's fine.
我们把热功率降到700  保持住
We take it down to 700, hold it there,
剩下的就交给斯托利楚克还有科什鲍姆  但是
the rest is Stolyarchuk and Kirschenbaum, but...
迪亚特洛夫会来监督
Dyatlov is gonna be supervising.
我要做件从来没做过的事
I have to do something I've never done before
而且迪亚特洛夫还要在身后盯着我
with Dyatlov looking over my shoulder?
别担心  我们一起来完成
Yeah, well, don't worry, we'll do it together.
我正在看操作指示呢
I'm looking at the instructions now.
我们要做那些吗
Are we supposed to do those or not?
喂  我是4号反应堆的阿基莫夫
Yes, this is Akimov in 4.
我手上有惰性发电测试的操作手册
I have the manual for the rundown test.
去年你们做过
You did it last year.
对  程序里有如何操作的指示
Yes, in the program there's instructions of what to do,
但有很多东西被划掉了
and then, well, there's a lot of things crossed out.
我要...
What should I--?
那我应该...
Well, what should I--?
你确定吗
Are you sure?
好的  谢谢
Right. Thank you.
他说要我们按照被划掉的指示来操作
He says to follow the crossed-out instructions.
那为什么它们被划掉了呢
So then why are they crossed out?
我们已经可以进行测试了
We've been cleared to run the test.
1600兆瓦  很好
1600. Good.
我能否指望你们都清楚自己在干嘛
Now, is it too much to ask that you all know what you're doing?
-这个  -能  当然可以
- Well-- - Yes. Absolutely.
-斯托利楚克  -能
- Stolyarchuk? - Yes.
-科什鲍姆  -我还没看
- Kirschenbaum? - Uh, I haven't reviewed.
我们刚刚才知道
We only just found out really--
拿去  看吧
There, review it.
或者你就照我说的做
Or you can just do what I tell you.
我想哪怕像你这么蠢  也能做到吧
I think even you, stupid as you are, can manage that.
我们开始吧
Well, let's go.
反应堆还在运行的时候
I'm supposed to switch the
我就要把汽轮机关掉吗
turbine off while the reactor's still running?
-这样不对劲  -闭上嘴  好好干活
- This is not good-- - Shut the fuck up and do your job!
托普特诺夫  把功率降到700兆瓦
Toptunov, reduce power to 700.
我从来没在功率这么低的条件下操作过
I've never done this with the power so low before.
没事的  我跟你一起
It's okay. I'm with you.
正在将功率降至700兆瓦
Reducing power to 700.
我想请诸位想象一下尤里·加加林
I want you to think of Yuri Gagarin.
请想象一下  他对于自己进入太空的任务
I want you to imagine that he has been told nothing
一无所知
of his mission into space
就直接被送上了发射平台
until the moment that he is on the launch pad.
请想象他手中就只有
I want you to imagine that all he has
一份自己从未见过的指令清单
is a list of instructions that he has never seen before,
其中还有一些被划去了
some of which have been crossed out.
而这就是当时4号反应堆
This is exactly what was happening
控制室里所发生的事
in the control room of Reactor 4.
夜班的人并没有受过测试的训练
The night shift had not been trained to perform the experiment.
甚至都没人通知他们会有这测试
They hadn't even been warned it was happening.
列尼德·托普特诺夫
Leonid Toptunov,
那晚负责控制和稳定反应堆的
the operator responsible for controlling and stabilizing
那个操作员  他
the reactor that night was...
他才25岁
all of 25 years old.
而他在职的总共时长
And his total experience on the job?
也才四个月
Four months.
这是由延误造成的人员问题
This is the human problem created by the delay.
但在反应堆堆芯里
But inside the reactor core,
在原子之间的空隙中
in the space between the atoms themselves,
有更加危险的东西在逐步形成
something far more dangerous is forming.
一种毒素
A poison.
现在是凌晨12时28分
The time is 28 past midnight.
列加索夫同志
Comrade Legasov.
很高兴能在这儿见到一些
I'm pleased to see some of my colleagues here
我在库尔恰托夫原子能研究所和能源部的同事
from the Kurchatov Institute and Minenergo.
但是诸位不需要是核能科学家
But you don't need to be a nuclear scientist
也能理解切尔诺贝利发生的事
to understand what happened at Chernobyl.
你们只需要知道
You only need to know this:
在核反应堆中基本上
there are essentially two things that happen
只发生着两件事
inside a nuclear reactor.
产生核能的反应功率
The reactivity which generates power
要不然升高  要不然降低
either goes up, or it goes down.
升高
降低
就这么简单
That's it.
操作者只需要保持平衡
All the operators do is maintain balance.
铀燃料
Uranium fuel.
铀原子分裂碰撞的时候  反应功率升高
As uranium atoms split apart and collide, reactivity goes up.
但如果没有平衡好反应功率
But if you don't balance the reactivity,
它就会不断升高  所以
it never stops rising. So...
硼控制棒
Boron control rods.
他们能够降低反应性  就像汽车的刹车
They reduce reactivity like brakes on a car.
但是还要考虑第三个因素  水
But there's a third factor to consider: water.
水
冷水带走系统中的热量
Cool water takes heat out of the system.
与此同时水变成水蒸气  也是我们说的"空泡"
As it does, it turns to steam, or what we call a "void."
切尔诺贝利核电站使用的RBMK反应堆中
In an RBMK reactor of the type used at Chernobyl,
有个名词叫做"正空泡系数"
there's something called a "positive void coefficient."
这是什么意思
What does that mean?
这意味着系统内的蒸汽含量越多
It means that the more steam present within the system,
正空泡系数
反应性越高
the higher the reactivity,
意味着产生更多热量  意味着产生更多水蒸汽
which means more heat, which means more steam,
意味着
which means...
这样似乎出现了恶性循环
It would appear we have a vicious cycle on our hands.
确实如此  但还有...
And we would, were it not for this--
确实如此
And we would,
但还有这个
were it not for this:
负温度系数
the negative temperature coefficient.
当核燃料温度升高时
When nuclear fuel gets hotter,
反应就会变缓  所以
it gets less reactive, so...
燃料使反应性升高
fuel increases reactivity.
控制棒和水能够使之降低
Control rods and water reduce it.
蒸汽使之增加
Steam increases it,
而上升的温度能够使它降低
and the rise in temperature reduces it.
这就是看不见的舞蹈
This is the invisible dance
不产生烟雾和火焰  却能给整个城市供电
that powers entire cities without smoke or flame.
它的确很美
And it is beautiful
在一切都正常的时候
when things are normal.
铀分裂释放能量时
As uranium splits apart to release energy,
它就裂变成了新的原子  氙
it breaks down into a new element, xenon.
氙
氙使反应性降低
Xenon reduces reactivity.
这就是霍缪克同志提到的毒素
This is the poison Comrade Khomyuk mentioned.
当堆芯以全功率运转的时候
When the core is running at full power,
反应堆能产生足够中子抵消氙造成的毒化作用
it burns the xenon away before it can cause a problem.
但是因为延期
But because of the delay,
切尔诺贝利4号反应堆已经以一半的功率
Chernobyl Reactor 4 has been held at half power
运行了10小时
for ten hours.
氙没有被中和掉
The xenon did not burn away.
它慢慢积累  毒化了反应堆
It built up, poisoning the core.
我们开始失去平衡了
We're starting to lose balance.
12点28分时
At 28 minutes past midnight,
反应堆已经准备好降低功率
the reactor is now primed to slow down.
然而  不出一个小时  它就会爆炸
And yet, in less than an hour, it will explode.
如果你不能理解为什么一个失速的反应堆
If you can't understand how a stalled nuclear reactor
最终会爆炸  我不会怪你
could lead to an explosion, I don't blame you.
毕竟你们不是在核电站
After all, you don't work in the control room
控制室里工作的人
of a nuclear power plant.
但我们发现  在那里工作的人
But as it turned out, the men who did
也不明白
didn't understand it either.
现在放慢
Easy now.
往下调
Take it down.
好  就这样
Good. Like that.
你们现在应该完成了才对
You should have finished by now.
我们就是按照降低功率的流程做的
We're following protocol for reduction rate.
你们是在拖延
You're procrastinating.
这个核电站里
There are ten other men
有10个人早就能完成了
in this plant who would've done it already.
继续工作  你做得不错
Keep working. You're doing fine.
科什鲍姆  等这帮老太婆准备好了再来叫我
Kirschenbaum, come get me when these old women are ready.
好的  迪亚特洛夫同志
Yes, Comrade Dyatlov.
好的  非常缓慢地
Okay, very slow now.
我们把它降到七百
Let's ease it down to 700.
-慢点  -我没有动控制棒
- Slow. - I-I didn't move any rods there.
-这怎么回事  -我连碰都没碰
- What is this? - I'm not even touching it.
我们的操作没有问题  我想也许是堆芯毒化了
We did everything right. I think that maybe the core is poisoned.
如果你觉得堆芯毒化了
Well, if you thought the core was poisoned,
那你的操作就有问题
then you didn't do everything right,
因为你使我的反应堆窒息了
because you're choking my reactor!
让它重新运作起来
Get it back up!
我想如果我们关闭本地自动控制系统
Uh, I think if we turn off LAC,
也许能获得更多控制
it may be possible to get more control.
-就这么做  快点  -关闭本地自动控制系统
- Do it. Go. - Switch off local automatic control.
切换至人工控制  列尼德
Go to global. Leonid.
本地自动控制系统已关闭  人工控制已开启
LAC disabled. Global control activated.
你们做了什么
What did you do?
-我照你说的做的  我关闭了...  -自己看看
- I-I did what you said. I switched-- - Look at it!
-我不明白  -该死的菜鸟
- I don't understand.  - Fucking amateurs.
你们使反应堆熄火了
You stalled the reactor.
你们他妈是怎么得到这份工作的
How the fuck did you get this job?
迪亚特洛夫同志
Comrade Dyatlov--
你又要告诉我你的操作没有问题吗
You're gonna tell me you did everything right again,
你这个无能的混蛋
you incompetent asshole?
对于这个不理想的结果  我很抱歉
I apologize for this unsatisfactory result.
-你在做什么  -我们必须把反应堆完全关闭
- What are you doing? - We have to shut all the way down.
-不  -可能出现了氙气坑
- No.  - We could be in a xenon pit.
我们必须关闭反应堆  等待24小时
We have to shut down and wait for 24 hours.
不  我们今晚就完成测试  把功率提升到七百
No. We're doing the test tonight. Raise power to 700.
我们不能直接上调这么低的功率
We can't raise the power from here.
-这是规定  -别跟我提什么规定
- The rules-- - Don't talk to me about rules.
如果功率是从80%开始下降
If we fall from 80%--
不不  是从50%
No, no. We fell from 50%.
-50%更糟糕  -规定没说50%
- Fifty percent is worse! - The rules don't say 50!
-根本没有这种规定  -迪亚特洛夫同志
- There is no rule! - Comrade Dyatlov,
我非常抱歉  但你说的没道理
I apologize, but what you're saying makes no sense.
-提高功率  -不
- Raise the power. -No.
我不能这么做  这样不安全
I won't do it. It isn't safe.
安全第一  永远都是
Safety first. Always.
这句话我已经讲了25年
I've been saying that for 25 years.
这也是我做这份工作的时长  25年
That's how long I've done this job, 25 years.
-这比你工作的时间长吗  阿基莫夫  -是
- Is that longer than you, Akimov? - Yes.
-长得多吗  -是
- Is it much longer? - Yes.
你那时候还在你妈怀里吃奶吧
And you with your mother's tit barely out of your mouth?
所以  我说安全就安全
So if I say it's safe, it's safe.
如果你们两个不同意
And if the two of you disagree,
那你们以后不用  也不会在这里工作了
then you don't have to work here and you won't.
不只是这里  还有库尔斯克
But not just here. You won't work at Kursk
伊格纳利纳  列宁格勒  以及新沃罗涅日
or Ignalina or Leningrad or Novo-Voronezh.
你们别想在任何地方找到工作  我会确保这一点
You won't work anywhere ever again. I'll see to it.
我想你知道  我能确保这一点
I think you know I will see to it.
提高功率
Raise the power.
我需要你记录下自己的命令
I would like you to record your command.
提高功率
Raise the power.
一起操作
Together, then.
我没有在现场
I wasn't even there.
什么
What?
他们提高功率时  我没在控制室内
I wasn't in the room when they raised the power.
如果你没有在那  那么你在哪里
If you weren't there, then where were you?
列加索夫同志  你是证人  不是公诉人
Comrade Legasov, you are a witness, not a prosecutor.
这个问题由我来问
I will ask the questions here.
如果你当时不在控制室里  那你在哪
If you weren't in the room, then where were you?
在厕所
The toilet.
厕所
The toilet?
霍缪克同志询问了那晚
Comrade Khomyuk interviewed everyone
每一个在控制室里的人
who was in the control room that night.
他们的说法一致
They all told the same story.
"我就知道迪亚特洛夫的命令是错的
"I knew what Dyatlov ordered was wrong,
但如果我不照做  他说  我会被开除"
but if I didn't do what he said, I would be fired."
列尼德·托普特诺夫
Leonid Toptunov.
就在他死的前一天
One day before he died.
不  迪亚特洛夫同志  你当时在控制里
No, Comrade Dyatlov, you were in the room.
你下令让他们提高功率
You ordered them to raise the power.
这是事实
This is a fact.
现在休庭
Court is now in recess.
三十分钟
Thirty minutes.
你了解切尔诺贝利这地方吗
Do you know anything about this town, Chernobyl?
不太了解
Not really, no.
大部分都是犹太人和波兰人
It was mostly Jews and Poles.
犹太人在大屠杀中被杀害
The Jews were killed in pogroms,
斯大林强迫波兰人离开这里
and Stalin forced the Poles out.
然后纳粹来了  把剩下的人都杀死了
And then the Nazis came and killed whoever was left.
但在二战后
But after the war...
人们还是搬来这里居住
people came to live here anyway.
他们知道脚下的土地浸满了鲜血
They knew the ground under their feet was soaked in blood,
但他们不在乎
but they didn't care.
死去的犹太人和波兰人
Dead Jews, dead Poles.
但不是他们
But not them.
没人想过这种事会发生在他们身上
No one ever thinks it's going to happen to them.
结果还是发生了
And here we are.
还有多久
How much time?
也许一年
Maybe a year.
他们说这是...
They call it a...
他们说这是"慢性疾病"
They call it a "long illness."
我倒没觉得很慢
It doesn't seem very long to me.
我知道你和我说过  我也相信你
I know you told me, and I believed you.
但随着时间流逝  我以为
But time passed, and I thought,
这种事不会发生在我身上
it wouldn't happen to me.
我虚度了
I wasted it.
我虚度了光阴却碌碌无为
I wasted it all for nothing.
碌碌无为
For nothing?
你还记得我第一次打电话给你的那个早上
Do you remember that morning when I first called you,
我多么漫不经心
how unconcerned I was?
我不怎么相信克里姆林宫说的话
I don't believe much that comes out of the Kremlin,
但是当他们和我说
but when they told me
让我负责清理工作时
they were putting me in charge of the cleanup
说事情并不严重  我相信了
and they said it wasn't serious, I believed them.
你知道为什么吗
You know why?
因为他们让你来负责
Because they put you in charge.
是的
Yeah.
我是个无足轻重的人  瓦列利
I'm an inconsequential man, Valery.
我一直都是
That's all I've ever been.
我曾希望有一天我会有所作为  但却没有
I hoped that one day I would matter, but I didn't.
我只是站在那些大人物身边
I just stood next to people who did.
还有其他像我这样的科学家
There are other scientists like me.
他们任何一个人都能做我所做的事
Any one of them could have done what I did.
但是你
But you...
我们要求的一切  需要的一切
Everything we asked for, everything we needed.
人力  材料  月球车
Men, material, lunar rovers.
还有谁能做到这些事呢
Who else could have done these things?
他们能听到我说的话  但他们只听你的
They heard me, but they listened to you.
所有的部长和副部长
Of all the ministers and all the deputies--
以及一大群顺从的傻瓜
entire congregation of obedient fools--
他们错误地派了一个好人来
they mistakenly sent the one good man.
老天啊  鲍里斯
For god's sake, Boris,
你才是那个最重要的人
you were the one who mattered most.
它真好看
Ah, it's beautiful.
列加索夫同志
Comrade Legasov.
现在是凌晨0点38分
The time is 38 past midnight.
反应堆已经几乎关停了
The reactor is nearly shut down.
4号反应堆的操作人员
The operators of Reactor 4
走上了一条通往灾难的道路
are locked on a path that leads directly to disaster.
局势已无法扭转
There's no way to turn back.
他们还不知道  但是木已成舟
They do not yet know it, but the die is cast.
在30兆瓦时  氙气仍在不断产生
At 30 megawatts, xenon is still being created,
但并没有被中和掉
but none of it is burning away.
反应堆被毒素淹没了
The reactor is drowning in poison.
更糟糕的是  反应度的热量根本不足以
To make matters worse, the reactor isn't hot enough
产生足够的蒸汽
to produce sufficient steam.
从这个状态安全提高功率的方法只有一个
The only way to safely raise power from this state
就是在24小时之内慢慢提高
is to do it very, very slowly over the course of 24 hours.
但是迪亚特洛夫希望功率马上提升
But Dyatlov wants it done now.
阿基莫夫和托普特诺夫只有一个办法
Akimov and Toptunov have only one course of action.
他们开始抽出控制棒
They begin pulling control rods out.
一下抽出十多根
Dozens at a time.
抽出一半  抽出四分之三
Halfway out, three-quarters of the way out,
但功率仍然不变
still, the power does not budge.
所以他们开始把控制棒完全抽出来
So they begin pulling them all the way out.
四号反应堆有211根控制棒
There were 211 control rods in Reactor 4.
阿基莫夫和托普特诺夫完全抽出了205根
Akimov and Toptunov completely withdrew 205.
记住  控制棒是这辆汽车的"刹车"
Remember-- control rods are the brakes on this car.
211根控制棒中
Of 211 rods,
只有6根还留在反应堆里
only six now remain in the reactor.
至于燃料  已经冷却了
As for the fuel, it's gone cold,
所以负温度系数
so the negative temperature coefficient
不能再降低反应速率
is no longer weighing down the reactivity.
但即使如此  氙的毒化作用太强
But even still, the xenon poisoning is so strong,
他们尽了力也只将功率提升至200兆瓦
the best they can do is raise the power to 200 megawatts.
控制棒被抽了出来
The control rods are out.
自动应急系统已被断开
The emergency system has been disconnected.
唯一能约束反应堆的东西
The only thing keeping the reactor in check
就是水和氙气
is water and xenon.
现在是凌晨一点  还有几分钟就要开始测试了
It's one in the morning. The test is minutes away.
对不起  但我们只能做到这样了
I'm sorry, this is all we can get.
现在是200兆瓦
It's 200 megawatts.
我们几乎把所有控制棒都拔出来了
We've pulled almost everything out.
如果只能这样的话  那就这样吧
If that's all we have, that's all we have.
但测试需要700兆瓦
But the test requires 700.
斯托利楚克  我们做好准备
Stolyarchuk, let's get ready.
-打开4号循环泵  -别  等一下
- Switch on pump 4. - No, wait a second.
-斯托利楚克  -我们的蒸汽量已经不够了
- Stolyarchuk-- - We have barely enough steam as it is.
汽轮机转得太慢了
The turbine is going too slow
测试无法给出任何有效结果
for the test to deliver any valid results.
-够了  -如果我们加入更多的水
- It's enough. - And if we add more water,
就会让它更慢...
there will be even less--
我说可以了  我知道我在做什么
I said it's enough. I know what I'm doing.
斯托利楚克
Stolyarchuk.
4号主循环泵  已连接
Main Pump 4, connected.
我们应该警告霍登楚克  管子会...
We should warn Khodemchuk. The pipes are gonna be--
别管他了  科什鲍姆
Never mind him. Kirschenbaum?
分离桶里的蒸汽气压太低了  只有五个大气压
The steam in the separator drum is too low-- five atmospheres.
好  我们来帮帮他  想办法把气压弄上来
All right, let's all help him. Get it up as best you can.
我们应该停下
We should stop.
把那玩意儿关了
Turn that fucking thing off.
你们有15分钟
You have 15 minutes.
15分钟
Fifteen minutes.
有15天也改变不了什么
They may as well have had 15 days.
他们所面临的问题无法解决
The problem they were facing was not solvable.
功率太低  水位太高
The power was too low, the water was too high.
测试已经被毁了
The test was already ruined.
结果已经没用了
The results would have been useless,
但迪亚特洛夫不在乎
but Dyatlov didn't care.
他只想要一份完整的测试报告
All he wanted to do was report a completed test.
凌晨1点22分
1:22 A.M.
离爆炸不到两分钟
Less than two minutes remain.
尤夫钦科  机械工程师  在他办公室
Yuvchenko, a mechanical engineer, is in his office.
佩罗沃钦科  反应堆工头
Perevozchenko, reactor section foreman,
在燃料房
is in the refueling hall,
在万吨钢制反应堆顶盖上方
high above the 1,000-ton steel reactor cover.
迪塔耶科和霍登楚克
Degtaryenko and Khodemchuk,
循环操作员  在泵室
circulation operators, are in the pump room.
他们没人知道这项测试
None of them have been told about the test.
他们都不清楚将会发生什么
None of them know what is about to happen.
凌晨1点22分30秒
At 1:22:30,
托普特诺夫看到一份
Toptunov sees a report
反应堆SKALA计算机系统发出的报告
from the reactor's SKALA computer system.
由于没有足够的控制棒
Based on the absence of sufficient control rods,
计算机建议关闭反应堆
the computer is recommending that the reactor be shut down.
当然会这么说
Well, of course it's saying that.
它不知道我们在测试
It doesn't know we're running a test.
好了  同志们
All right, comrades.
再过几分钟  就可以结束了
Another few minutes, it will all be over.
科什鲍姆  你准备好就开始
Kirschenbaum, when you're ready.
我们的操作没有问题
We did everything right.
示波器打开
Oscillograph on.
关闭8号节流阀
Closing Number 8 throttle valve.
发电机转子开始减速
Generator rotor beginning rundown.
凌晨1点23分04秒
1:23:04.
他们做的每个决定
With every decision,
都让这个反应堆像弹弓一样被拉开
they have pulled this reactor back like a slingshot,
拉得比任何人都开
further than anyone has ever pulled,
现在测试开始了
now the test begins.
水泵停了  他们放手了
The pumps are shut down, and they've let go.
水泵停止向反应堆输水
The pumps stop moving water through the reactor.
铀燃料现在不受新冷却剂控制
Uranium fuel is now unchecked by fresh coolant,
不受控制棒控制
unchecked by control rods.
平衡立刻偏向了另一边
The balance immediately swings in the opposite direction.
不到一秒内
In less than a second,
反应性开始增加
reactivity increases.
在堆芯内部
Inside the core,
剩余的水迅速转为蒸汽
the remaining water is quickly converting to steam.
出现了一个空泡
A void is being created.
却没有水输入填补它
There is no fresh water to replace it.
蒸汽增加反应性
Steam increases reactivity,
增加热量  又产生蒸汽
increases heat, increases steam,
增加反应性
increases reactivity.
剩余氙气持续衰变
The remaining xenon decays away.
功率上升
The power is rising.
没什么可以阻止了
There's nothing left to stop it.
凌晨1点23分35秒
1:23:35.
功率激增  萨沙
We have a power surge! Sasha!
你做了什么
What did you do?!
凌晨1点23分40秒
1:23:40.
全世界的所有核反应堆的所有控制室里
In every control room of every nuclear reactor in the world,
有一个按钮  它只有一个用途
there is a button with one single purpose
"紧急停堆"  或立即停止反应堆运行
to "scram," or instantly shut down, the reaction.
在苏联核反应堆设备中  这个按钮叫AZ-5
In Soviet reactors, that button is called AZ-5.
一旦按下AZ-5  所有控制棒会立即插入
You press AZ-5, all of the control rods insert at once,
核反应也会立刻停止
and the reaction is stopped dead.
但是...
But...
你在等什么  列加索夫  说谎啊
What are you waiting for, Legasov? Tell your lies.
迪亚特洛夫同志  这是你的最后一次警告
Comrade Dyatlov, you will not be warned again.
-不然呢  -消停点吧  迪亚特洛夫
- Or what? - For god's sake, Dyatlov.
列加索夫已经暴露了
Legasov's already given it away.
他之前就说了
He said before,
-迪亚特洛夫同志  -没办法阻止爆炸的发生
- Comrade Dyatlov. - there was no way to avoid what was coming.
-他知道内幕  她也知道  -迪亚特洛夫同志
- He knows something. She knows something. - Comrade Dyatlov.
我知道你是什么货色  瓦列利·阿列克谢维奇
I know what you are, Valery Alexeyevich.
-你是个骗子  -今天我们听得够多了
- You're a liar. - We've heard enough for today.
被告将还押候审
The defendants will be remanded in custody.
-本庭...  -我还没说完
- Court will-- - I... I haven't finished.
我还有更多证据
I still have more evidence to give.
不用了  你的证词已经完整了
It's not necessary. Your testimony is concluded.
-法官阁下  -本庭休庭
- Your Honor. - Court is now adjourned.
-明天继续...  -让他说完
- We will resume tomorrow with-- - Let him finish.
谢比纳同志
Comrade Shcherbina...
让他说完
Let him finish.
迪亚特洛夫破坏了所有规则
Dyatlov broke every rule we have.
他将反应堆状态推向了毁灭边缘
He pushed a reactor to the brink of destruction.
他这么做是因为他确信核反应堆有保险装置
He did these things believing there was a failsafe.
AZ-5  一个能停止一切反应的按钮
AZ-5, a simple button to shut it all down.
但在他所制造的情形下  已不存在保险装置
But in the circumstances he created, there wasn't.
紧急停机系统有个致命的缺陷
The shutdown system had a fatal flaw.
在凌晨1点23分40秒
At 1:23:40,
阿基莫夫按下了AZ-5
Akimov engages AZ-5.
被完全拔出的控制棒
The fully-withdrawn control rods
开始重新插入反应堆
begin moving back into the reactor.
这些控制棒是硼制的  硼能减弱核反应
These rods are made of boron, which reduces reactivity,
但控制棒的尖端不是
but not their tips.
尖端是石墨制  而石墨会加快核反应速率
The tips are made of graphite, which accelerates reactivity.
为什么
Why?
和我们的核反应堆
For the same reason our reactors
没有反应堆安全壳的原因一样
do not have containment buildings around them,
西方国家都有
like those in the West.
和我们的堆芯
For the same reason we don't use
不使用适当浓缩的燃料原因一样
properly enriched fuel in our cores.
和我们是唯一一个核反应堆
For the same reason we are the only nation
使用流水冷却  用石墨做缓和剂
that builds water-cooled, graphite-moderated reactors
带有正空泡系数的国家一样
with a positive void coefficient.
更便宜
It's cheaper.
首先与堆芯接触的控制棒部份
The first part of the rods that enter the core
是尖端的石墨
are the graphite tips.
当发生接触后  堆芯在持续加剧的
And when they do, the reaction in the core,
核反应  瞬间激增
which had been rising, skyrockets.
液态水的所有分子
Every last molecule of liquid water
瞬间汽化为蒸汽
instantly converts to steam,
使得大批燃料管道膨胀并破裂
which expands and ruptures a series of fuel rod channels.
这些管道里的控制棒已无法再插入
The control rods in those channels can move no further.
石墨尖端被固定
The graphite tips are fixed in position,
导致无止境地加速核反应
endlessly accelerating the reaction.
切尔诺贝利4号反应堆此时就是个核弹
Chernobyl Reactor 4 is now a nuclear bomb.
凌晨1点23分42秒
1:23:42.
佩罗沃钦科往下看
Perevozchenko looks down
那巨大的反应堆钢盖
on the enormous steel lid of the reactor...
看到了难以置信的景象
...and sees the impossible.
每个重达350公斤的
The control rod and fuel channel caps,
控制棒和燃料管道盖子
which each weigh 350 kilograms,
正上下跳动着
are jumping up and down.
他跑去警告控制室
He runs to warn the control room.
但他已经无法阻止即将发生的事情
But there's nothing he can do to stop what is coming.
1点23分44秒
1:23:44.
蒸汽鼓破了更多燃料管道
The steam blows more fuel channels apart.
我们不知道功率究竟达到了多高
We do not know how high the power went.
我们只知道最后的读数
We only know the final reading.
4号反应堆
Reactor 4,
原额定功率为3200兆瓦
designed to operate at 3200 megawatts,
最后超过了33000兆瓦
went beyond 33,000.
堆芯再无法承受如此巨大的压力
The pressure inside the core can no longer be held back.
最终  导致了
At long last, we have arrived.
1点23分45秒的大爆炸
1:23:45, explosion.
在反应堆盖子被掀开的瞬间
In the instant the lid is thrown off the reactor,
氧气冲了进来
oxygen rushes in.
与氢和过热的石墨混合
It combines with hydrogen and super-heated graphite.
灾难链在此时也构建完成了
The chain of disaster is now complete.
迪亚特洛夫同志
Comrade Dyatlov!
那一晚在控制室里
No one in the room that night knew
谁也不知道紧急停机按钮相当于引爆器
the shutdown button could act as a detonator.
他们并不知道
They didn't know it,
因为这一点被刻意隐瞒了
because it was kept from them.
列加索夫同志  这和你
Comrade Legasov, you're contradicting
在维也纳的证词自相矛盾
your own testimony in Vienna.
我在维也纳撒谎了
My testimony in Vienna was a lie.
我向全世界撒了谎
I lied to the world.
我不是唯一一个保守这个秘密的人
I'm not the only one who kept this secret.
还有许多人
There are many.
我们都只是服从命令
We were following orders,
服从克格勃  服从中央委员会
from the KGB, from the Central Committee.
而现在  苏联境内还有16个反应堆
And right now, there are 16 reactors in the Soviet Union
有着同样的致命缺陷
with the same fatal flaw.
其中三个就在距离切尔诺贝利
Three of them are still running
不到20公里的地方运行着
less than 20 kilometers away at Chernobyl.
列加索夫教授  如果您的意思是
Professor Legasov, if you mean to suggest the Soviet State
苏联应对所发生的一切负责
is somehow responsible for what happened,
那我必须警告您  您的立场很危险
then I must warn you, you are treading on dangerous ground.
我已经身处危险的地方了
I've already trod on dangerous ground.
我们现在就在危险的地方
We're on dangerous ground right now,
就因为我们的秘密和谎言
because of our secrets and our lies.
它们几乎定义了我们
They're practically what define us.
当事与愿违  我们用谎言编织谎言
When the truth offends, we lie and lie
直到我们忘记真相的存在
until we can no longer remember it is even there.
可真相就在那里
But it is still there.
我们每撒一个谎  就欠真理一条债
Every lie we tell incurs a debt to the truth.
而这债  迟早是要还的
Sooner or later, that debt is paid.
这就是RBMK反应堆堆芯爆炸的原因
That is how an RBMK reactor core explodes.
谎言
Lies.
瓦列利·阿列克谢维奇·列加索夫
Valery Alexeyevich Legasov,
父亲是阿列克谢·列加索夫
son of Alexei Legasov,
中央委员会意识形态合规部部长
Head of Ideological Compliance, Central Committee.
你知道你父亲在那里做什么吗
Do you know what your father did there?
知道
Yes.
学生时期  你是苏共青年团的领导
As a student, you had a leadership position in Komsomol.
共青团  对吗
Communist Youth, correct?
-知道还问  -回答问题
- You already know. - Answer the question.
是的
Yes.
在库尔恰托夫原子能研究所
At the Kurchatov Institute,
你曾任党委书记
you were the Communist Party secretary.
你在位时  限制了犹太裔科学家的晋升
In the position, you limited the promotion of Jewish scientists.
是的
Yes.
以取悦克里姆林宫官员
To curry favor with Kremlin officials.
你和我们是一路人  列加索夫
You're one of us, Legasov.
我可以随意处置你
I can do anything I want with you.
但我最想告诉你  我很清楚
But what I want most is for you to know that I know.
你不勇敢
You're not brave.
也不是英雄
You're not heroic.
你只是个忘了自己身份的垂死之人
You're just a dying man who forgot himself.
我知道我是怎样的人  也知道自己做过什么
I know who I am, and I know what I've done.
在公正的世界里  我会因为撒谎被枪毙
In a just world, I'd be shot for my lies,
而不是因为道出了真相
but not for this, not for the truth.
科学家
Scientists...
痴迷于理性的愚蠢执念
and your idiot obsessions with reasons.
当子弹击穿你的头骨时
When the bullet hits your skull,
原因还重要吗
what will it matter why?
没人会被枪毙  列加索夫
No one's getting shot, Legasov.
你在维也纳已经举世闻名了
The whole world saw you in Vienna.
现在杀了你的话会让我们很难堪
It would be embarrassing to kill you now.
而且有什么意义呢
And for what?
你今天的证言不会被国家接受
Your testimony today will not be accepted by the State.
也不会被媒体报导
It will not be disseminated in the press.
就像你根本没说过一样
It never happened.
不  你会活着
No, you will live,
能活多久活多久
however long you have,
但你不再是科学家了
but not as a scientist, not anymore.
你能保留职位和办公室
You'll keep your title and your office,
但没有工作  没有权力  没有朋友
but no duties, no authority, no friends.
没人会和你说话
No one will talk to you.
也没人会听你说话
No one will listen to you.
其他那些不如你的人
Other men, lesser men,
将会获得本属于你的荣誉
will receive credit for the things you have done.
你的贡献现在成了他们的贡献
Your legacy is now their legacy.
你会活着见到这一幕
You'll live long enough to see that.
谢比纳在这件事中扮演了什么角色
What role did Shcherbina play in this?
他没有参与
None.
他并不知道我要说什么
He didn't know what I was gonna say.
霍缪克呢
What role did Khomyuk play in this?
她也没有参与
None.
她也不知道
She didn't know either.
考虑到你今天的所作所为
After all you've said and done today,
如果你选择现在撒谎就太奇怪了
it would be curious if you chose this moment to lie.
像你这样见多识广的人
I would think a man of your experience
应该听得出我有没有撒谎吧
would know a lie when he hears one.
你不能再和他们两个见面或交流
You will not meet or communicate with either one of them ever again.
你也不能再和切尔诺贝利事件有关人员交流
You will not communicate with anyone about Chernobyl ever again.
你将成为一个无关紧要的人
You will remain so immaterial to the world around you
到你死去的那天
that when you finally do die,
就仿佛你从未出生过一样
it will be exceedingly hard to know that you ever lived at all.
如果我拒绝呢
What if I refuse?
为什么要担心不会发生的事情呢
Why worry about something that isn't going to happen?
"为什么要担心不会发生的事情呢"
"Why worry about something that isn't going to happen?"
真是太棒了
Oh, that's perfect.
他们应该把这句话印在钞票上
They should put that on our money.
科学家都是天真的
To be a scientist is to be naive.
我们过于关注对真相的追寻
We are so focused on our search for truth,
却没考虑过鲜有人想让我们发现真相
we fail to consider how few actually want us to find it.
但真相就在那里  不管我们是否发现
But it is always there, whether we see it or not,
不管我们选择看还是不看
whether we choose to or not.
真相不会在乎我们的需求或想法
The truth doesn't care about our needs or wants.
也不会在乎我们的政府  意识形态或宗教
It doesn't care about our governments, our ideologies, our religions.
它会永远在那里等着被发现
It will lie in wait for all time.
这是切尔诺贝利事故留下的礼物
And this, at last, is the gift of Chernobyl.
我曾经害怕真相的代价
Where I once would fear the cost of truth,
现在我只会问
now I only ask:
谎言的代价是什么
What is the cost of lies?
瓦列利·列加索夫于1988年4月26日自杀
享年51岁  当天恰好是切尔诺贝利核泄漏事故两周年整
列加索夫的回忆录录音带在苏维埃科学界流传
他的自杀让这些录音带无法被忽略
受其死亡事件的影响  苏维埃官员终于承认
RBMK反应堆的设计缺陷
剩下的反应堆都做了改进
以防止类似切尔诺贝利的事故再次发生
在切尔诺贝利事件中
列加索夫曾获得数十名科学家孜孜不倦的帮助
有些人公开反对官方的说法
并因此被告发  逮捕或监禁
乌拉娜·霍缪克是个虚构角色  代表了他们所有人
向他们对真相和人类的奉献致敬
鲍里斯·谢比纳于1990年8月22日去世
距他被派往切尔诺贝利已过去4年零4个月
鉴于他们在切尔诺贝利灾难中所扮演的角色
维克多·布卡诺夫  安纳托利·迪亚特洛夫  尼克莱·福明被判劳改十年
尼克莱·福明在被释放后
去了俄罗斯加里宁的一座核电站工作
安纳托利·迪亚特洛夫因辐射相关的疾病
于1995年去世  享年64岁
瓦列利·霍登楚克的遗体至今仍未被发现
他被永远埋在4号反应堆下
消防员们穿过的衣服还留在普里皮亚季医院的地下室
至今残存的放射量依然很危险
在丈夫和女儿惨死后  柳德米拉·伊格纳滕科多次中风
医生告诉她  她再也无法怀孕
但他们错了
她后来跟她的儿子在基辅生活
那些在铁路桥上围观的人群  据称一个都没有活下来
现在这座桥被称为死亡桥
400名矿工夜以继日地工作了一个月  防止核熔毁灾难
据估计其中至少100人没能活过40岁
媒体曾广泛报道称
潜入水下抽空起泡池的三名潜水员英勇牺牲
实际上他们经治疗活了下来
有两人甚至活到了今日
超过60万人被征召去隔离区内做清理工作
尽管其中大批人因为辐射染上了疾病或死亡
但苏维埃政府没有记录这些人的命运
乌克兰和白俄罗斯被污染的地区  也就是"隔离区"
范围为2600平方公里
大约30万人被迫永久离开家园
他们当时被告知这只是暂时的  但直到现在仍被禁止返回
米哈伊尔·戈尔巴乔夫一直担任苏联最高领袖
直到苏联1991年解体
2006年时  他写到
"切尔诺贝利的核熔毁事故  或许是苏联解体的真正起因"
2017年切尔诺贝利新石棺终于完工
耗费近20亿美元  预计可使用100年
核爆炸事故后  乌克兰和白俄罗斯人民的癌症率骤升
上升最快的人群是儿童
我们永远无法确切知道切尔诺贝利事故导致多少人死亡
大多数人估计是4000到9.3万人
苏联官方公布的数据  自1987年就没变过
是31人
谨以此纪念那些受难和牺牲的人